[Music]
Stanford
University all right so we
were in the midst of talking about
symmetry symmetries are operations that
you can do on a
system which don't change the
description which don't
change the
phenomena which don't change the energy
levels which don't change the values of
the energies of systems that that's not
ours I don't
think in particular they don't change
the values of the energies of a system
examples that we talked about were
translation if you take an atom with a
given energy and you move it from one
place to another the energy doesn't
change doesn't matter which atomic State
you study it's not just true for the
ground state it's true true for every
Atomic
State and
so the hamiltonian doesn't
change when you move things that's a
symmetry the schinger equation doesn't
change same schinger
equation same thing is true for rotating
a system we're going to talk a lot
tonight about rotating systems
uh another example is just interchanging
two particles two identical particles
you might call one electron electron one
the other electron electron two you
might call them Harry and
Fred uh changing the names of the
electrons interchanging electron one
with electron two doesn't
change the uh properties of an atom
so that's also a
symmetry we tend not to think of it as a
symmetry just because we're so used to
it identical particles are identical so
it doesn't matter what you name them but
it is a symmetry and there are other
symmetries of
physics uh for example if you have a
crystal lattice a crystal lattice has a
kind of translation
symmetry um it's not translation
symmetry in space it is translation
symmetry inace space but a different
kind of translation and symmetry of
space it's just translating everything
by one lattice unit if we had a very
very long almost infinite
um uh Crystal then it's almost a perfect
symmetry to translate from one atom to
the you know from uh to translate the
whole system by one lce spacing of
course there it's not exactly a symmetry
if the system is not infinite if the
system is not infinite and there are
boundaries to the crystal well then you
can't really translate it but if the
crystal went on and on and on
forever then you could do two things you
could
imagine taking the
Crystal and moving the entire Crystal a
little
bit this one goes to here this one goes
to here this one goes to here this one
goes to
here that is a symmetry of a crystal
that's true it's a symmetry of anything
the ability to move it from one place to
another but the crystal has a different
symmetry which is
just just
translating from let's call this 1 2 3
four and let's suppose it goes on and on
and on forever and ever just relabeling
the crystal so that this one is now
called minus one this one is called no
no not one minus one 0 1 2 three
Imagining the crystal goes on and
on that's also a symmetry translation of
crystals by the crystal uh by the
crystal lattice
spacing what else what are the what are
the symmetries are there there are
lots there are lots but
um some of them were more abstract than
others
the physically intuitive ones tend to
have to do with properties of
space the homogeneity of space the fact
that every point is like every other
point is translation symmetry the
isotropy of space the fact that every
direction is like every other direction
is rotational
symmetry
now another concept
that is we'll see is related to symmetry
not the same thing is called
degeneracy degeneracy and then
specifically degeneracy of energy levels
degeneracy of energy levels is simply
the statement an energy level is of a
system is said to be degenerate if
there's more than one state with the
same energy
level then that energy level is called
degenerate
when does it happen I mean for a random
system with a generic
hamiltonian assuming that the spectrum
of it
is discrete Spectrum some sort of
discrete Spectrum um of energy levels it
would be an accident or would be a
rather odd accident that two levels
would have exactly the same energy and
when I say exactly I mean exactly the
same energy they may have the same
energy to one part in 10 to the 15th but
to say they have exactly the same energy
what kind of coincidence would that
take
well as we'll see it doesn't necessarily
take a coincidence it takes a
symmetry in fact those are the only
cases where we really believe that there
are true de degeneracies exactly
generaci of
nature when there are symmetries
degeneracies sometimes
no sometimes not degeneracy sometimes
mean symmetry the other way symmetries
sometimes imply degeneracy but not
always and I'm going to show you now I'm
going to begin with an example in which
um you can see sort of
intuitively how symmetries and when
symmetries imply
degeneracy that incidentally is one of
the main uses of
symmetry to analyze the energy spectrums
of systems and see that they have levels
that uh that exactly match that can be
very important in atoms it's extremely
important um let's start with rotation
symmetry let's start with rotation
Symmetry and I want want to think about
a very simple system namely a particle
moving on a
circle it could be a particle moving on
a circular wire I don't want it to get
off the circle so it's a little particle
which is kind of a bead moving on the
circle and what is the Symmetry the
Symmetry is rotational
invariance how do we describe the
location of the
particle
well if we embed it in two-dimensional
space then we could describe it by an X
and a y
coordinate but as long as a particle
can't get off the circle if it's only
moving in the angular
space then it's a little bit excessive
to think about an X and A
y-coordinate we can just think of a
Theta coordinate or an
angle that particle has a wave function
here's the particle of here it has a
wave function the wave function could be
thought of as a function of X and Y but
as I said that's excessive too much uh
too many variables we can just think of
it as s of
theta the wave
function it's square or it times its
absolute excuse me it times its complex
conjugate Dei defines the probability to
find particle on the
circle
what does the operation of rotation do
let's say
rotation uh
counterclockwise rotation
counterclockwise takes
s to S of theta minus Epsilon where
Epsilon is a small angle of
rotation I constantly get confused about
whether it's plus Epsilon or minus
Epsilon I hope I have it right but if
not don't worry about it it just means
all of my signs will be
wrong
okay so s goes to S of theta minus
Epsilon or another way to say the same
thing is that the change in
s Epsilon of course is our um small
number which is so small that its square
is
zero it's an infinite decimal number the
change in s is equal to the derivative
of s with respect to
Theta time
Epsilon I can rewrite
that as- I
Epsilon
Time - I Epsilon minus I derivative of
with respect to Theta
now I've put those eyes in there
because I want you to remember well
let's think about ordinary momentum
ordinary
momentum is
um described by an operator which is
minus i d by
DX angular
momentum is simply basically the same as
momentum except the coordinate is angle
instead of being linear
position the operator minus i d by D
Theta that's an operator it's a linear
operator it's a Herm Mission operator
the I is there to make it her
Mission without the eye it would not be
her mission one of those eyes be
positive is one of the eyes
what do I have a I think the minus I to
minus I yeah I think it may be plus
let's see did I get it
wrong no I I I actually had it
right uh minus I had it right I had this
this side was wrong yeah okay uh it's
it's correct
now okay
but minus i d by D Theta is a Herm
Mission
operator you may want you may be
surprised that there has to have a i in
front of it for it to be her mission
after all her mission is the analog
among operators of as being real but I
guarantee you that I has to be there go
back in your notes to the study of
momentum and you'll find out why that
eye has to be there and that's called
the angular
momentum that's usually denoted
l y l don't know y
l y p for momentum don't know why P for
momentum but L is the angular momentum
and so we can write that the change in
s under the operation of infinite tmal
rotation is governed
by minus I
times the action of the angular momentum
operator on
S that identifies according to the
definitions of last week that identifies
L as the generator of
rotations if you can't remember the
precise definition let's just say that
this is the
definition of the generator of a
symmetry object operation if the
Symmetry operation is such that it has a
version of it for arbitrarily small
parameter in this case angle then the
definition of the generator is just in
terms of the small change in the wave
function when you shift by an infinite
decimal
amount and that will just give you the
generator don't I did lose an Epsilon
right I did lose an Epsilon and this
defines L and L is minus i d by D
Theta okay and L is known as the angular
momentum now before I go on I want to
put in some H
bars uh I'll I'll surely drop them again
but just to remind you where they
go the precise definition including HS
when we don't set H bar to one contains
an har bar over
here that's the same har bar that occurs
in the momentum P = Min - I HR d by
DX same
HR and
um it's a little bit arbitrary where we
put
it but putting it over here I guess we
would say that the change in
SI I Epsilon over H bar * l i probably
here and there just to remind you and to
keep your uh to keep you awake I will
put in h
bars now and then every so often
randomly
okay what are the igen vectors of the
angular
momentum the igen vectors of the Ang and
the igen values the igen values are the
values are the possible outcomes of
experiments and the igen vectors are the
states of the system which for which
those outcomes are
certain all right to answer that we
write the equation L on
S that's the action of the angular
momentum is equal
to an igen value I'm going to call that
igen value
M it's standard M *
s now if I were doing it I would have
put little L here but somebody did this
long in the past M happens to stand for
magnetic quantum number but uh that's a
historical anachronism nevertheless the
igen value of and let's let's add a
little more to this picture let's put a
z-axis in the z-axis comes out of the
Blackboard so we're talking about
rotations about the
z-axis we could call this the Z
component of the of the angular momentum
it is the Z component of the angular
momentum for the moment I'm going to
suppress
that all right and M is the igen value
of that angular momentum so strictly
speaking it's the igen value of the Z
component of angular momentum does it
matter which axis is z and which axis is
X or you rotate the home no it doesn't
matter but it's
convention okay how do we find the igen
vectors in other words how do we find
the wave functions that correspond to
igen vectors and for that we just do the
obvious thing we put in minus I HR d by
D
Theta that's
L acting on S of theta
is equal to m s of
theta that's a standard type of equation
the derivative of something is
proportional to that something else we
could bring the IH bar over to the right
hand side and that tells us that the
igen vector with igen value
m is equal to e to the i m Theta
very similar to the case of ordinary
momentum oops what do I have missing
here I'm missing the har bar the har bar
would go downstairs
here because if you divide by H bar you
see the thing that comes in is M over
har
bar now unlike the case of ordinary
linear momentum there's another
constraint you know the other constraint
I'm sure that most of you know it but
let's spell it out anyway the other
constraint is that when Theta is equal
to
2i the wave function should be exactly
what it was when Theta was equal to zero
why because going around by 2 pi brings
you back to the same point and so if
there's a sensible wave function that
sensible wave function should be
unchanged if you go around the circle by
2 pi so that says that e to the i m over
H bar * 2 pi well let's see first of
all the wave function for Theta equal
Z is just one if I set Theta equal to
Zer this is just one if I go around by 2
pi the answer will be e to the i 2 pi m/
HR and that also has to be equal to
one what's the constraint the constraint
is that M over H bar has to be an
integer in order to make sure that the
wave function comes back to itself that
it's single valued that it has a
definite value at each point it's
necessary that the igen values M be
integer multiples of plunk constant so
let's write that
out
m is equal to an
integer
no
yeah m is an integer time H bar but the
usual notation usual
definition is to set m equal to the
integer just call M the integer and then
the angular
momentum the igen value of the angular
momentum is an
integer time H
bar okay that's the quantization of
angular momentum in units of har
bar Hereafter for at least for a time
being I will drop
H and we'll just say that the angular
momentum must be equal to an
integer angular momentum must be equal
to an integer and that's
a fundamental fact of quantum
mechanics that
uh we've known since the time of
um of Neil's
bore okay now I have H the following
question for
you must it be the case let's suppose
there's some
energy and let's suppose the energy
depends on the angular momentum of
course it does the energy the bigger the
angular momentum the bigger the energy
particles whipping around with a large
angular momentum it has more energy than
if a small angular momentum so we expect
that the angular
momentum that the energy will depend on
the angular
momentum but must it be must it
be that the angular moment that the
energy
of a state with angular momentum M
that's the igen value must it be the
same as the energy of a state with
angular momentum minus
M what's the difference between M and
minus M well the only difference is that
Ang positive angular momentum means the
particle is going around the
circle
counterclockwise and negative angular
momentum means it's going around
clockwise I'll take a vote how many
people think that the energy must be the
same for M and minus
M of course I'll raise my hand too how
many think it does not have to be the
same I will also raise my
hand question yeah um just when you
start out side goes to side thus
should I think that then that implies
we're we're looking at it it's going in
a clockwise Direction not telling you
anything about the direction of motion
of the particle it's only telling you
which way you counted the feder as
positive it's just tell it's like
telling you I've decided that the
positive x-axis points that way that
tells me nothing about whether I'm
walking that way or I'm walking this
way right it does it does set the
definition of what you mean by positive
and negative angular
momentum but it does not tell you
whether the system has positive or
negative angular
momentum okay art you raised your hand
the second time you know an example
where uh I was just thinking that you
know you could have a SYM an
asymmetrical field somewhere okay right
anybody know an example of a Sim of a
field which would um lead to an
asymmetry between positive and negative
angular momentum or angular
velocity magnetic field for electron
yeah a magnetic field if there were a
magnetic
field that's exactly what magnetic
fields do magnetic field for
example magnetic field into the
Blackboard will raise the energy a
little bit maybe I I may have backward
raise the energy a little bit of
positive angular momentum and lower the
energy a little bit of negative angular
momentum and it will break the
degeneracy it'll break the degeneracy
between M and minus M that's the
language if you didn't have the magnetic
field the energy
levels would be degenerate in
pairs angular momentum zero Ang would oh
angular momentum zero would not be
degenerate there's only one of them but
angular momentum plus one and minus one
would be degenerate angular momentum 2
and minus two would be degenerate in the
presence of the magnetic field that
degeneracy is broken but that magnetic
field does not violate in any way
rotational
invariance the magnetic field is
pointing into the Blackboard it doesn't
in any way violate the invariance with
respect to
rotation and so we see
that um symmetry is itself not enough
not this symmetry rotation Symmetry by
itself is not enough to tell you that
the energy levels are
degenerate why am I even talking about
it
well you need to add if you add one more
symmetry one more symmetry is enough to
tell you that the energy levels have to
be degenerate the Symmetry is very
simple it's not a continuous symmetry
it's a discrete symmetry it's simply the
discrete symmetry of reflection about
one of the
axes reflection about an axis is
basically mirror reflection imagine you
had a horizontal mirror here and any
system Above The Mirror Has a mirror
image below the
mirror and if there's mirror symmetry
it's not called mirror symmetry it's
called reflection
symmetry I'm going to call it mirror
symmetry and use the notation M to
describe that symmetry the reason is I
don't want to use R for reflection
because I don't want you to confuse it
with
rotation so M Big M big m stands for
reflection about a
mirror and in particular we could
imagine the mirror is oriented
along the the x
axis of course the mirror is
two-dimensional but in in uh in this
situation along the XZ plane but we
don't have to think about Z we just have
a mirror
and the mirror image
of I don't know if I can draw the mirror
image of
that I don't think I
can
did I get that
right maybe not I don't know the the
mirror image
of this is
this
okay all
right if there is not mirror symmetry in
a
problem then a configuration like this
whatever it happens to be I don't know
what it is it's a couple of building
blocks or something uh the energy of
this does not have to be the same as the
energy of
that if there is if the Symmetry if
there is no mirror symmetry in the
system but if there is mirror symmetry
it means that the description of this
and the description of this are
indistinguishable and that they must
have the same
energy so let's add mirror
symmetry to rotation Symmetry and see
what we buy from it well we will
certainly find that the energy levels of
the energy levels e of
M must be the same as e of minus M why
is
that let's think about in the upper half
plane
here let's think of a circular motion
moving
counterclockwise what's the mirror image
of that
that's a circular motion moving
clockwise so the mirror image of
a particle moving with positive angular
momentum is a particle moving with
negative angular momentum and if the
world or our system has such a mirror
symmetry such a reflection symmetry then
it means that the energies of the same
of the two states must be exactly the
same there we have an example where
rotation
symmetry which tells you that the energy
levels depend on the energy in a well
that that they depend on the angular
momentum and that the angular momentum
is conserved the added ingredient is the
mirror symmetry which tells you that the
energy levels have to be
degenerate so that's a case in which two
symmetries combined tells you that there
have to be degenerate energy levels
question yes if we if the position of
the particle is determined by the
probability IE by the square of the S we
look at s uh which and think of the more
expression with the cosine and we change
M to minus M uh and you do the algebra
at least it seems that I in my head but
it seems like the sign goes away and
you're left with the same number so in a
way replacing M with minus M
algebraically will show that it is a
same same probability meaning it's uh
they're equal the energies are equal is
that not a good way to look at
it it's just
wrong
um a function of theta is not the same
as a function of minus
Theta for
example here's a function of theta the
probability is concentrated over here
here's a corresponding function of minus
Theta the it's over here they're not the
same
thing also e to the I Theta is or e to
the i m Theta is not the same is e to
the minus I in Theta but the square yes
yes yes but we don't but
that's right but the
square this is the equation for the igen
vectors of Sai or the igen vectors of
angular momentum it involves s it
doesn't involve SAR
s
yeah that's the whole point of quantum
mechanics we have to work with wave
functions not
probabilities so is it the case that um
miror symmetry guaranteed degeneracy in
any situation no no no it
doesn't it doesn't in itself it what's
necessary is to have two
symmetries and one more condition that
the two symmetries don't commute with
each
other that the Symmetry operations for
the two symmetries don't commute with
each
other I'm going to let you prove that
that if symmetries don't commute with
each other that it implies degeneracy
it's not hard to prove but I'm going to
show you how it works in a couple of
examples that's any two symmetry any two
symmetries if they don't Comm commute
with each
other so let's ask whether rotation
Symmetry and reflection symmetry
incidentally um the term mirror symmetry
happens to have another meaning in
physics it's a very fancy uh term very
mathematical term that applies to
certain manifolds and string theory
don't get confused by it it's a
completely different concept I just use
mirror to represent the reflection in
space yeah the miror Symmetry the magne
yes very interesting good good point
yeah the mirror symmetry of a magnetic
field the mirror inversion of a magnetic
field is a magnetic field pointing in
the other
direction if you take a a um magnetic
field pointing into into the
Blackboard and you reflect the
configuration about
a uh plane like this what you get is a
configuration with the magnetic field
coming out of the Blackboard this is
because magnetic field is an axial
Vector okay you can see it another
way magnetic fields are made by currents
current let's let's not imagine that the
magnetic field is there let's instead
imagine that the magnetic field is being
made by a current going this
way a current going around in a loop
like this it could be going around a
solenoid we could be talking about a
solenoid into the Blackboard with the
current going
clockwise that creates a magnetic field
going into the
Blackboard on the lower half plane the
mirror image of that is a solenoid in
which the current is going in the
opposite
direction and because the current is
going in the opposite direction it makes
a magnetic field pointing out of the
Blackboard so yes the
um the mirror inversion of a magnetic
field is not the same magnetic field so
I think you foresaw that that had to be
the case if uh
if
um yeah
okay all right let's ask let's ask the
mathematical let's go through the
mathematics now of showing that
reflection mirror reflection does not
commute with rotation and we'll do that
by showing that the generator of
rotation doesn't
commute with the action of the
reflection
operator we need to figure out what the
reflection operator
does okay the reflection operator will
call M for Mirror it takes any wave
function and replaces it I shouldn't
write Arrow I should write
equals and replaces it by wave function
of minus
Theta reflection about the horizontal
axis just takes Theta to minus
Theta so any wave function when you
reflect it goes the S of minus Theta
okay and in particular if you apply it
to e well all right we'll do it in a
minute now let's
consider the
commutator of the mirror symmetry
transformation with the angular momentum
the angular momentum is just a version
of a rotation operator for very small
rotation let's consider the
commutator
okay what the commutator is telling us
about is what happens if we do the two
operations in opposite order a rotation
about an axis and a reflection versus a
reflection and a rotation about the same
axis are they the same operations
rotating about an axis and then
reflecting is that the same as
reflecting and then rotating okay the
answer is obviously no well if it's not
obvious to you think about it but we'll
work it out by doing the mathematical
commutator and seeing what we get let's
look
at the commutator of M with L we know
what L does here it is it differentiates
with respect to Theta what does m do it
reflects Theta so we can figure out what
the commutator does we can figure out
what it does when it acts on a wave
function I'm going to act on a
particular wave function I'm going to
act on the wave function e to the
i m
Theta
a igen vector of the angular momentum
I'm leaving H bar out of it we don't
need it and don't confuse Big M with
little M Little M and Big M have nothing
to do with each other this stands for
Mirror this stands for magnetic quantum
number okay let's see if we can work it
out let's first do
ml * e to the I IM Theta what does l do
when it hits e to the I IM Theta
brings an M down it brings an M
down right it just brings an M down so
this gives
us M * little m e to the I
Theta and what does capital M
do when it hits e to the I IM
Theta it just changes the sign of
theta incidentally once this is just a
number it doesn't matter which order Big
M and Little M
appear and so this is just equal to
Little M time eus I M
Theta the Big M just reflected
Theta okay let's do it in the opposite
order l
m e to the I
Theta now in the opposite
order first M
acts and that gives us
L when M acts it changes the S of theta
and gives us e to Theus I IM
Theta but what happens when L hits e to
the minus I
Theta anybody got a good
idea it brings down a minus
M by reflecting we've changed the sign
of the angular momentum so the angular
momentum operator gives us the minus of
what it gave before it gives us minus m
eus i IM
Theta so the answer is that M and L
angular momentum and the reflection
operator don't commute with each
other that's the key to whether or not
symmetries
um
whether or not symmetries create
degeneracies of energy levels we've seen
in this case that two symmetries
rotational symmetry together with
reflection symmetry tell us that there
are degeneracies of the energy levels
that M and minus M have to have the same
energy that's a pattern it's also a
theorem but um we'll I don't think we'll
do the theorem right now
so does does this mean that any
Heisenberg pair
generates
DeGeneres
um a Heisenberg pair like X and P well
the problem is that X andp are not
conserved right and they're not
symmetries in
themselves in this in the case of um in
the case of a particle not having a
magnetic
field then angular momentum rotation and
reflection are both symmetries they both
commute with a hamiltonian they both um
they both are
conserved X and P are typically and
generally not uh not conserved if they
were then the answer would be
yes then the answer would be yes yeah
okay we're going to study an example in
in some detail tonight I think we'll get
through it
oh let's well let's let's just uh write
down just some formal observations of
what I mean supposing you have two
symmetries now what does it mean to have
a symmetry let's call the two symmetries
A and
B the A and B stand for
operators operators that act on the
state vectors they could stand for
infinitesimal generators or they could
stand for the full um operation of the
symmetry A and B let's say they refer to
the generators let's take the case of
where there are small versions of the uh
of the
Transformations
then to say the symmetries means that
both of them commute with a
hamiltonian it does not in itself say
that a commutes with b and in general
here's an example where they
didn't commutator of a with
B may be
nonzero and there are two
possibilities both possibilities will
lead to degeneracies but let's think of
two possibilities in one possibility the
commutator of A and B may be a itself it
may be B itself or it may maybe some
linear combination of A and B that does
not lead to a new symmetry it just it
doesn't lead to a new operator it just
leads to a linear combination of the old
ones but let's suppose that it leads to
a genuinely new operator that cannot be
written as a linear combination of A and
B let's call it
C okay first theorem theorem it's not
hard it's not a theorem it's hardly a
theorem C also commutes with h how do I
know
um let's put an i in here why am I
putting an i in
there the commutator of two Herm Mission
operators is not Herm Mission it's
anti-mission it's like the commutator of
X and P is I if you want the hermiss
operator you have to put an i here so
let's suppose that c is the commutator
of A and B except with an extra r
then C is a Herm Mission
operator and let me show you why it's
conserved it's conserved for a trivial
reason let's think about the commutator
of C with h that's
AB H minus H AB
right AB is equal to C apart from a
factor of
I so the commutator of C with a H is
proportional to abh minus
H but now all we have to do is say look
we know that b commutes with h that's an
assumption that means that we can move B
to the other side once we've moved B to
the other side we know that a commutes
with h that's also an assumption so we
can move a to the other
side and that of course is equal to zero
so if a and b both commute to the
hamiltonian
then the commutator
of
uh of A and B also commute with a
hamiltonian in fact the product A and B
commute with a hamiltonian but the
reason we don't consider the commutator
is because the sorry the product of A
and B commute with a
hamiltonian certainly the commutator
does okay uh I'm not so interested in
the product because it's not generally
her Miss it's the commutator which is
her Mission so there's an
example where given two symmetries if
they don't commute you generate a third
Symmetry and it might be an independent
one might be a new
thing all right once you have a and b
and c you can play the game again
commute C with A and
B see what you get you may get something
that just reproduced es or that's just a
linear combination of the three that you
started
with or you may get something new you
may get
D you keep doing this and doing this and
doing this until you don't get something
new you might never end you might get an
infinite number of different
symmetries that's rare and that's
unusual and it's
bizarre or it will close
eventually and you'll have some finite
number of symmetry R
trees which are all independent of each
other and which form a kind of closed
system when you commute
them when you commute the
generators question yeah I just to make
sure I understand your argument what you
showed was that uh if you have a and b
that commute with h then the product a
commutes with it does and and then since
the commutator of a is just a minus ba
that you'll get the commentation
yeah right So
eventually if you have a few symmetries
you can start commuting them and
commuting them among themselves being
guaranteed that what you get is another
symmetry which may be just a trivial
superposition of the of the original
ones or it may be something new if it's
something new good put it into your uh
list and commute it some more
eventually you'll either run out of them
or you won't but I'm particularly
interested in the situations where you
run out and then you have what is called
a commutator algebra the commutator
algebra includes the commutators of all
the
symmetries and it includes the
commutation relations with the
hamiltonian which just say
zero when you're in that situation
whenever that happens you have a great
deal of power over the system to be able
to say a lot about the nature of the
energy levels and degeneracies among
[Music]
them okay so that's that's the general
oh what is what is such a structure
called the the collection of symmetry
operations a group this is a symmetry
group this is a symmetry
group why why do we care that uh
these two things are degenerate what why
do we care that it's degenerate or not
it would certainly be important if for
example we wanted to know if from one
state you could emit a photon and go
down to the other state can't do it if
the energies are the
same we want to classify the energy
levels of
systems why because we're
spectroscopists and we want to study the
spectroscopy of uh of
atoms oh a spectroscopist and we want to
study the way um hadrons excited states
of hadrons emit pons or
whatever same
rules so the commut the elements of so
each of these commutators would be an
element of this symmetry well the these
things themselves these these I imagined
were
generators the generators form an
algebra a commutator algebra Lee
algebra
the Gen the the symmetries themselves
which are built up from the generators
by applying small Transformations
repeatedly those are the group elements
but we're going to mainly work with the
uh with the
generators the generators have a lot of
power the algebra of them
aat comination yeah they're all they're
all
yep right they're all
now you can have a situation where you
may have many symmetries but they
commute with each other that can
happen uh then you don't get then you
don't get anything terribly interesting
you just have separate symmetries that
commute with each other symmetries of
that kind are called ailion a bilion
means everything commutes with
everything else when there are nonzero
commutators between symmetry generators
it's called
nonilon is there any fun the definition
of a generator
again a generator of a symmetry is if
you take the Symmetry operations and you
unitary symmetry operations and you
consider the case of a symmetry
operation very close to the identity in
the case of rotations it means a
rotation by a very small angle and you
write it in the form one I can never
remember I think it's minus
i g * eps on then G is called the
generator okay you can build up if you
know the generator that allows you to
make a small
rotation if you keep doing small
rotations repeatedly about a given axis
you'll eventually build up a whole
rotation I mean a finite
rotation so the generators contain
basically all the interesting
information about the
group well
almost is there any fundamental
difference between a b and then C or D
no so we could have started with b and c
and then a yeah well maybe yes maybe no
you might take B and
C and you might not get a you might get
D you might or you might get a plus b if
you got a plus b then it wouldn't be
anything
new you might get a plus b plus C back
again it still wouldn't be anything new
but if you got something new D which was
not among your previous list then you
have a genuinely new
symmetry question yeah um could you
please repeat what you said about what's
an algebra that's not a
question that's a direct
story what what did you ask me no what
did you tell me what do you what did you
request me you said something was an
algebra and I want first of all I want
to know what it is the algebra and what
is what is the the algebra is the
collection of
generators you can add them they are
still
generators you can subtract them you can
even multiply them by ordinary numbers
and you can commute them so Comm
commuting is is product in that algebra
that's correct okay commuting is a
product in that algebra and albra is a
thing is a collection of elements that
you can add you can multiply by numbers
and you can multiply sorry and you can
multiply by each other in this
algebra
multiplication is commutation that's
correct that's
correct okay so we'd like an
example not only we like an example we
would like the preeminent most important
example and that is angular momentum and
rotation about different
axes as an example of what I'm talking
about here we can consider rotation
about the x-axis which way is the x-axis
that way I guess rotation about the
x-axis rotation about the y
axis and if you think about it then you
probably know this I can never do this
I'm not going to try it but you know if
you do rotate about the x-axis then
rotate about the y axis by the right
amount what you get is a rotation about
the
z-axis
what's
more if you rotate a little bit about
the x- axis and then a little bit about
the Y AIS no a little bit about the
x-axis and then a little bit about the
y- axis it's not the same as rotating a
little bit about the y- axis first and
then about the x-axis they don't commute
with each other we're going to show
that we're going to show that by
studying the commutation relations of
the angular
momentum you look puzzled I'm puzzled
because I know that that's true for
finite rotations but I thought somehow
that infinitesimal
rotations
infinite
okay they don't commute the second order
in the small numbers
yeah uh that's enough that's enough but
the group but the remember these
generators have the small numbers
factored out of
them and they don't commute they really
don't commute okay we're going to we're
going to work out an example in detail
we we do it right now
the example is the three components of
angular momentum the three components of
angular momentum form a the three comp
rotations about any axis form a
group but for our purposes now we've not
concentrating on groups the angular
momentum generators form a Lee algebra a
commutator algebra that simply means
that the commutators of components of
the angular momenta give you other
components of the angular moment
momentum and we'll work that out but
first let's uh talk a little bit
about classical angular momentum for a
minute just to to understand the
corresponding classical
concept uh okay we can do
this okay let's imagine
a planetary
orbit for my purpose now it can be a
circular orbit it's orbiting about an
axis and it has an angular momentum
which is perpendicular to the orbit I
could be
LZ it has a certain energy
e question at a classical level is that
energy level degenerate the meaning of
that is is there another orbit with
exactly the same
energy of course there's a many other
orbits with exactly the same energy but
in particular there's some that you can
easily prove have the same energy
because of rotational invariance all you
have to do is rotate this about an axis
let's rotate it
about the Y
AIS take this configuration rotate it
about the y
axis it's a new
configuration and the angular momentum
has changed
oops Yeah I guess that's okay I guess
what did I do I don't like my picture my
picture this is in the wrong place it
should be coming from
here there's
LZ and now there's a change in L it's
picked up an X component yes in fact
it's picked up an X component and so
because of rotation about the Y
AIS rotation about the y
axis has not only given us another
configuration with the same energy but
it's going given us a configuration with
a shift of the angular momentum and in
particular a shift of the X component of
the angular
momentum classically that's an
indication that Quantum mechanically the
components of angular momentum don't
commute and a rotation by
one a rotation of a component of an
angular momentum about a different axis
changes the angular momentum about the
third
axis that uh has a great deal to do with
the commutation relations of
rotations but we'll work it out in
detail so here's an example classical
physics just at the classical level the
combination of rotation and
variance rotation and variance the
combination of the different rotation
and variances about different axes tells
us unequivocally that there must be
degeneracy of the orbits that there must
be orbits with the same
energy uh with rotated angular
momentum that's that's the basic idea
classically so let's go through it
quantum mechanically the first thing we
have to do is understand the angular
momentum generators
better so let's come back to the angular
momentum generators they form
previously I just said minus i d by D
Theta but
let's let's work them out not assuming
that a particle is moving on a circle
but that a particle could be moving in
three dimensions in fact it doesn't even
really have to be a particle but let it
be a particle a particle moving in three
dimensions first before we do three
dimensions let's do two dimensions
particle moving in the XY plane not
restricted to a
circle and let's ask what's the
generator of rotation now it's not ID
well may be ID by D Theta but we can
represent it in terms of the XY
coordinates all right so here's the
position of the particle let's say let's
suppose we rotate the the
configuration rotating the configuration
whatever it happens to be means whatever
the particle is or whatever the wave
function of it is shift it
so if the particle was at Point
XY it moves to a new to a new
Point what's the new point the new point
is given if the old point was given by
XY then the new point is shifted by an
amount Delta X and Delta y I'm assuming
that the angle is
small and let's call the angle Epsilon
let's call the
angle
Epsilon then what is Delta X and Delta y
I'll leave it to you to prove this is
this is a very simple exercise it's just
simple
geometry for a small
Epsilon can anybody tell me what Delta X
is it's of course proportional to
Epsilon minus
y if Y is
positive and you wrot rotate the change
in X is negative so it's got to be minus
and it's proportional to
y what about my Delta
y That's Epsilon *
X okay now let's consider a wave
function s of X and
Y what is the change in the wave
function if you reconfigure the the
system by rotation
it's
equal to the derivative of s with
respect to x times the change in
X plus the derivative of s with respect
to
Y times the change in
y if I shift the wave
function but Delta X is minus Epsilon *
y
minus
Epsilon *
Y and this is plus
X that's the change in the wave function
and of course this must
be by
definition I guess it's l
subz time
s so oh EP I Epsilon I Epsilon time
LZ now it's much too late in the evening
for me to follow the signs so I won't
I'll leave the signs for you to uh to
figure out yourself
but uh it has this form but what is the
side by DX in quantum
mechanics I *
PX so this is another factor of
I and this
is y *
PX did it matter which order I put down
Y and PX
here do they
commute yeah y commutes with PX X
doesn't commute with PX y doesn't
commute with py but x commutes with
py what about this one this one is plus
I times x
py all
times all right apart from a sign which
I said I wouldn't try to track in any
detail it's quite clear what the
correspondence between the Z component
of the angular
momentum the generator of
rotations and the coordinates and
momenta of the particle R
LZ is to be identified with X pyus Y PX
and now I do have this is the right
sign I lost track of the sign but this
is the correct sign have you seen that
before that's the component of R cross P
the standard three-dimensional angular
momentum R cross
P so now we see a new interpretation of
R cross
P not just um the mechanical angular
momentum from classical physics but it
now has the role of the thing which
generates small
rotations by acting on the wave
function
okay what about the other components of
angular momentum you can read them off
just by cycling by cycling through the
XY z x goes to y y goes to z z goes to
X all right so going through
it Z goes to x x goes to y y goes to
Z minus Z
py and
LX
XYZ py pz
PX minus
xpy these of course you could confirm by
doing by imagining rotations about the
other axes but just just by you know
just by the um parallel reasoning this
is what you would
get
questions pz oh you're right pz I have
two different notations for Z don't
I yeah wait a
minute which one which
one l y good thank you l y good good
good good good
okay these are the these
are are they
symmetries well they're symmetries if
the system is rotationally
invariant
why well because rotating a system
shouldn't change the
hamiltonian so we expect we fully expect
that if we have a system with rotational
invariance then these should commute
with a hamiltonian and typically they do
they do in fact they always do if the
system has
invariance um what kind of systems have
rotational
invariance well the a very particular
system is a particle moving in a central
force
field a particle moving in a central
force field will have rotational
invariance and therefore for that kind
of system the commutator of L x with h
equals z and in fact all three of
them elab one 12 and 3 or X Y and Z they
all commute with the hamiltonian and
they're all conserved and this is just
good old angular momentum conservation
except in a Quantum uh
guys next
question do they commute with each other
suppose all we had was LX and ly that's
all we knew about it LX and l y why we
only knew about LX and l y I don't know
our mothers only told us about X and
Y
uh would we discover
LZ that LZ is another
symmetry well our mothers only told us
about X and Y but they also told us
about commuting the generators of Le
groups so mom tells us look
commute LX and ly and see what you get
let's commute LX and ly and see what we
get okay I what do we need to do we need
to know the commutation relations
between X Y and Z on the one hand and PX
py and pz on the other hand the rule
I'll write it over here uh any x with Y
or Z or anything like that is always
equal to zero x with itself is equal to
zero x with Y X with Z is equal to zero
they commute P's commute with each other
PX py and pz all commute with each other
which things don't commute the things
that don't
commute are X with
PX and that's equal to I strictly I * H
bar same with
y
y with
py is I and Z with pz is I I won't write
it
down how about x with
py that commutes multiplication by X and
d and differentiation with respect to Y
commute with each other and you can
check
that okay so let's calculate the
commutator of LX with l y That's the
commutator of
ypz minus
zpy
comma comma for
commutator
zpx minus
xpz now I'm not going to go through the
rules for commutators if you remember
them you don't but I'll just but it's
it's it's by inspection you can more
oress see what to
do who in this side doesn't commute with
who on this this side it's a commutator
of this thing with this thing what on
this side doesn't commute with something
on this side well y commutes with z y
commutes with PX and so forth but pz
does not commute with Z so there's two
things which don't
commute and let's see over here Z
doesn't commute with
pz with
pz those are the only common
combinations if we were to expand this
out the only combinations which don't
commute are pz did I get it with
z
and Z did I get that
right zpx -
x no
no what have I written
here what am I doing I'm commuting
LX that looks right ypz minus
zpy with ly which is zpx minus xpz yeah
that's
right yeah
okay okay all right from this term over
here you get a commutator of pz with Z
what's the commutator of pz with
z I minus
I minus I so there's a minus
I and that gets rid of pz and z and you
left over with Y
times no y sorry left over that gets rid
of Z with pz and that leaves over Y and
PX from this with this you get y * PX
does it matter which order you write
down Y and PX no okay so there's minus i
y * PX and then there's the other one
which
is commutator of Z with pz is again I
and now we
get plus
I xpy I
believe yeah x * py where is
it i' ah
x * py from
here which is our
friend
I time l
z so this is an example of
commuting generators and discovering new
generators not a big surprise but
nevertheless we see it before our eyes
and so now we can write write down the
general list of commutation relations
notice that by commuting two angular
momentum we got a third one there's only
three there's no way we're going to get
more than three generators out of this
sequence of
commutations and so the Lee algebra is
just going to be the Lee algebra of the
three components of the angular momentum
Let's uh let's write it
down this one says
that l l x with l
y equals I
LZ and then the trick is always the same
just
cycle L L equal I L L L = I L brackets
brackets
comma x y
z y y z
x z x
y those are our basic commutation
relations of angular momentum if
you continue commuting you won't get
anything
new so we've discovered a genuine Le
algebra yeah generated LC don't you have
to prove that it's not your combination
of LX and
L well you oh you want to you you want
to prove that LZ is not a linear com
yeah I suppose we
do
um but yeah I think we can prove that
let's see what can we
do
um let me not answer that right now it
gets me off track they should
be
Let's
uh let's come back to
it I it should be very
easy I don't want to get I don't want to
get my head uh confused of course the Z
component of the angular momentum is not
likely to be a linear combination of X
and Y components but yes you're right
you're right we do have the obligation
of showing that
LZ um is not you know what I think we
can probably show that LZ from these
commutation relations I believe we could
show that LZ does not commute with any
linear combination of LX and
ly
if uh if
LZ was a linear combination of LX and l
y it would commute with that linear
combination I think we can prove
ital what does that mean LC isal what
does that mean
lar
combination what does it mean that the
Alex
is yes they are components they are
perpendicular components of some
three-dimensional Vector R cross P but I
don't want to use that I think the right
thing to do is exactly as this uh
gentleman said is to directly prove
algebraically that LZ is not a linear
combination of of the others and I think
I think we can prove that but
yeah algebra what's that what do you
mean by a algebra another algebra a Lee
algebra is an algebra where the rule for
multiplication is
commutation okay that's what it means
that's that's but don't worry about the
name the name is just it just it's it's
a collection of objects whose
commutation relations close a collection
of objects when you keep commuting them
you don't get new ones that's called the
Le
algebra and
um it's just a
name Lee of course was a
mathematician
and I don't know was algebra a
mathematician it might have been I don't
know alab yeah I think he
was
alra what's that Arabic word isn't it
what's that algebra is an Arabic word I
think it's an Arabic word
yeah I think it was I think I have a
feeling his name was just Al
jaabir but I'm not sure I I I remember
reading that but maybe I don't remember
reading
it okay so where are we we have this
nice collection of algebraic relations
including three more but I'll just write
them as one
more the commutator of any component of
L with the hamiltonian is equal to
zero which means that the three
components of angular momentum are
conserved okay what can we do with
that
well a
lot
this is a good time to remember what we
learned about the harmonic oscillator by
having a similar kind of algebraic
structure the similar kind of algebraic
structure that we had were the
commutation relations of creation
operators Annihilation operators and the
number
operator we had closed commutation
relations of a very similar kind not
exactly the same kind but closed
commutation
relations and they were quite
powerful we deduced the entire spectrum
of the harmonic oscillator we did it
from constructing creation and
Annihilation operators it was much
easier than solving any schinger
equation we're going to do the same
thing here we're going to construct
creation and Annihilation operators but
the creation and Annihilation operators
are not going to change the energy what
they're going to change is the Z
component of angular momentum now why do
I pick the Z component of angular
momentum that's
arbitrary remember in quantum mechanics
if you want to actually work with things
you usually have to pick a basis you
usually have to pick a a uh a preferred
set of
operators which uh you regard as um
as defining a
basis often it doesn't matter there the
X basis or the X representation not a
basis a
representation in quantum mechanics of a
particle is the position representation
there's the momentum
representation in studying spins we had
the sigma Z representation and the sigma
X representation and so
forth it really doesn't matter for the
purposes of the invariant physics which
basis you use use but it's common to
pick one and work with it and keep with
it we're going to do the same thing here
we're going to pick out the Z component
of angular momentum uh to focus on
there's there's nothing special about it
we could have picked the X and we could
have picked the Y but it's useful to
pick the Z
component no more useful than X and Y
but let's do
it okay so we're going to work with the
Z component of angular
momentum as and its igen
vectors we're going to work with Z
component of the angular momentum and
its igen vectors and see what we can
find out about the entire
um
Spectrum
okay LZ has igen vectors it's a Herm
Mission operator how many it has I don't
know we'll find out as we go along and
let's call the igen value of LZ Little M
it's the same igen value of the same
notation that I used in two
dimensions in two Dimensions where there
was only the Z component of angular
momentum I call the igen values M and
I'll continue to do
that again it's a historical
notation it had to do with putting atoms
in magnetic field
you put an atom in a magnetic field and
you study its
spectroscopy and arbitrarily the Z
Direction was chosen for the direction
of the magnetic field and the angular
momentum about the z-axis was called the
magnetic quantum number but uh for our
purposes now m is just an igen value of
L
subz this is the equation that says that
the igen vector m is an igen Vector of L
subz with igen value Little M sort of
redundant notation I've used the same
notation for the igen vector and the
igen value and here's where
mathematicians go crazy because they
don't like you to use the same notation
for two
things
um but we'll do it anyway okay so that's
the that's and what we want to find out
is what are the possible values of n
M the possible values of M will be
exactly the same as the possible Von
values of L subx and L suby because
there's nothing special about L subz but
nevertheless let's see what we can find
out now in the case of the harmonic
oscillator we figured stuff out by
inventing creation and Annihilation
operators or operators which raised and
lowered the energy we're now going to
invent operators which raise and lower m
they raise and lower the magnetic
quantum number and how do you do it you
do it in a way very similar to the
harmonic oscillator question yeah when
you refer to we did the harmonic
oscillator you talked about theal
harmonic ill we
did or the or the uh the quantum
harmonic oscillator okay we never did
that we didn't we didn't do that not in
the class not not in the last class but
it's in the book and there is and there
is a video that covers it o somewhere
back in history oh we didn't we never
did the harmonic oscillator okay in that
case we'll come back to the harmonic
oscillator and instead of telling you
how much this is like the harmonic
oscillator I will tell you how much the
harmonic oscillator is like angular
momentum
good
we this is self-contained it doesn't
require us to no I thought that was one
of your main motivations for this for
the second course because you said Gee
we didn't get to cover the harmonic
isolator I
forgotten well it's in our book but
uh is I'll set the link out the video
the
book
onemail okay do not worry about the
harmonic oscillator now it's much more
complicated than
this
so we've picked out LZ as a little bit
special not physically but
mathematically for our purposes and
let's invent operators
LX Plus i l
y and also LX minus i l
y and call them
l+ and L
minus and what I want to figure out is
the commutation relations
of l+ and L minus with
LZ for the moment I don't really care
too much about the commutator of l+ with
L minus I'll tell you now it's LZ but
um that's not so important what I want
is the commutation relations of l+ with
L minus so how do we get them well um
we're going to get them from the last
two of these equations let's rewrite
them
let's see how do I write
them LX with
LZ that's this one over
here I've changed the order of x and z
so that's minus i l y do I have that
right yeah
that's this one over
here and since I changed the order of x
and z that changes the sign then there's
the other one commutator of l y with
LZ and that
is or I ly with
LZ we have to do a little bit of work
here's l y with LZ multiply it by I and
we get at minus
LX and now we're just going to add and
subtract these two equations adding and
subtracting them will give us the
commutation relations between l+ and L
minus on the one hand and
LZ minus LX
yeah okay we add them and subtract them
if we add them we get l+ commuted with
LZ and if we subtract them we get L
minus we do the summation on this side
also and here's what we get I'll just
write it out we don't need to belabor it
the commutator of l+ with
LZ
is -
l+ and the commutator of L
minus with
LZ is L minus not minus L minus but plus
L minus L
minus those are the two basic
commutation relations that follow from
these now I understand this is very
abstract how did anybody know to do this
well
um I'm not even sure who did it it's
probably Direct
D had a weird mind and uh he
uh and he liked to
commute he didn't live in the Bay
Area I can't tell you exactly why he did
this but uh but you know once you do it
you say wow okay that's that's very
clever so this is just another way of
writing Le algebra it's probably true
that commutator of l+ with L minus is
LZ uh you can or maybe twice LZ you can
work that out but we won't use it okay
now what I'm going to prove is the
following very interesting little
theorem supposing we have an igen Vector
of M of
LZ supposing we have one we found one
somehow now I'm going to show you how to
find another one with a different igen
value
okay we're going to do it by applying
one of these equations which one are we
going to do l+ let's do l+ we're going
to take this equation for l+ and
multiply it by the igen vector M by this
little igen Vector M so let's work work
work it
out
l+ L
minus sorry l+
LZ minus LZ l+ that's the
commutator acting on the vector
m is
equal to minus l+ acting on the vector
M okay so what do we
know let's take this
first term well okay let's take this
first term here on the left what does LZ
do when it hits
M multiplies by
m that's because m is an igen Vector of
LZ so the first term becomes
M time L + m I'm going to take l+ and M
and I'm going to put them in a red
circle
because I want you to think of it as a
unit
now
let's
add this over to the left side here
we're going to take this term and move
it to the right and we're going to take
this one and move it to the left so
let's take this one and move it over to
the left that will give us
plus l+ m
that's also exactly the same thing that
appears in the red
circle so what do we get we get m +
1 times the object in the red
circle let's
just draw a red circle
there that's the left hand side
with this term transposed to the left
now let's transpose the other term to
the right that's equal to
LZ time l+
M but l+ m is again exactly the thing in
the red
circle thing in the red circle is a
certain K
Vector so what does it say this
says that there's another igen Vector of
LZ this equation is an igen vector
equation for LZ LZ acting on the red
igen Vector gives us m+ one times the
red igen Vector what does this mean it
means we've discovered another igen
Vector of LZ with igen value m +
one we can call the thing in the Red
Bracket here we can just call it the
igen vector M
+1 we found a trick for taking any en
Vector of LZ and promoting it lifting it
up one unit and increasing the igen
value by one
unit what about if we did the same thing
with L
minus if we did the same thing with L
minus we would again discover another
igen Vector with one lower
unit
so we've used the simple algebra of
commutators to generate a spectrum a
spectrum of values of
LZ and much more they're separated by an
integer they're separated by integers so
we've discovered the following fact that
if we plot on the vertical axis here the
possible values the values of
M or LZ LZ the possible values of LZ if
we find one at some value of M oh let's
let's first of all let's
um let's put some let's lay some
integers
down 0
1 2 3 0 -1 - 2 -
3 Let's suppose we found an igen Vector
an igen value of M nothing has told us
it must be an integer so it could be
anywhere it could be over here it could
be at 3/4 or it could be at 78 or it
could be Pi quarters or it could be a
half it could be
anywhere not over here let's put it over
here
then just one question I thought the M
was the way it was defined it had to be
an integer going all the way back in
fact we're going to find it has to
be
yeah you're right you're right except
not quite oh what I mean is I thought
you already said that yeah we could go
back to what I said earlier and use that
I don't want to I don't want to because
I want to show you another argument for
it now the other argument will not prove
it's an integer it'll prove something a
little bit looser and the looser fact is
in fact the correct fact but we'll see
all right so the first thing is we know
that there's got to be another one above
it one unit above it and another one one
unit below
it now there's one exception to this
statement that when we apply
l+ we will necessarily get a new igen
Vector with one unit up what's the other
alternative
possibility Z that you get zero that you
get just plain zero no Vector at all so
this could terminate conceivably it
could
terminate I wish I had a green pen I
don't it could terminate somewhere let's
say it terminates
here and by the same logic it could
terminate from below if L
minus killed the
vector so we will generate a
family which may or may not also
terminate somewhere
now the first thing which is true is
there a Rel if it terminates if it
terminates then there's a relationship
about where it terminates from above and
below and the reason is very
simple m is the igen value of
LZ remember we have rotation invariance
supposing I Ed my rotation invariance to
completely rotate by 18
80° if I rotate by
180° then LZ becomes minus
LZ if there's really rotational symmetry
then it must mean the Spectrum the
possible igen values of LZ must be the
same as the igen values of minus LZ it's
just looking at the same system except
standing on your head and if there's
rotation and variance you should get
exactly the same Spectrum so so from
that you can conclude that this Red Dot
and this red dot have to be
symmetrically
placed there's only two
possibilities if the red dots are
symmetrically placed and these are and
these are separated by integers then
there's only two
possibilities the first possibility is
that the Red Dot is at an
integer let's call this this is the
integer
M and zero 1 2 3 1 2
3 down
here symmetrically replac symmetrically
placed about the origin and separated by
integers that would be one one possible
Spectrum 1 2 3 0 1 2
3 if it
terminates there's another possibility
and the other possibility that still is
consistent with a symmetric spectrum and
Separation by integers and that's the
half integer
option is zero
again one two
whatever
whatever start
here shift by an integer Shi shift by an
integer shift by an
integer let's see here's zero 1 2 3 1 2
3 and it's also symmetrically placed
about the
origin in this spectrum over here if
it's physically
reasonable the values of the angular
momentum the Z component of the angular
momentum are half
integers half integer three Hales 5
Hales minus a half - 3- five halves
ending
somewhere or the other possibility is
integer
Spectrum now you mentioned before that
uh that I'd already sort of proved that
uh that the spectrum is integer and I
did somebody mentioned you okay and
that's correct that is correct for
orbital angular momentum orbital angular
momentum means R cross P it means wave
functions of particles that depend on
position and how do we prove that you
remember how we proved it
oh we proved it by saying the wave
function has to be single valued when
you go
around when you go all the ways around
okay
so on the face of it it would seem that
this is the only physical
possibility in fact this possibility
here is also real and it corresponds to
spin angular momentum but for the time
being let's just get rid of it we'll
come back to
it all right there's a
Max
given a state like this we can generate
a few more it may or may not terminate
but let's assume it
terminates we found a multiplet of
States a multiplet of
states which are in some way related to
each
other
and which have to have the same energy
why do they have to have the same
energy let's prove they have the same
energy and then we'll quit that'll be
enough for tonight let's prove one more
thing they have to have the same
energy let's suppose that we found the
state M and it has an energy equal to e
* m it's an igen Vector of the energy it
has L subz equal to M and it has energy
e now let's go to m + 1 m +
1 is
l+ *
m that's M
+1 and let's ask what its energy is
so what do we do we apply the
hamiltonian to it and see what we
get okay but the hamiltonian commutes
it's assumed that the hamiltonian
commutes with all the components of the
angular
momentum so that means we can write that
this is the same as
l+ H *
m but H * m m is just e *
m what does this equation say it says h
on M +1 that's l+ on M is equal to
e * n +
1 we can do the same thing with n minus
one that tells us that if we find an
igen Vector of the angle of the Z
component of angle
momentum which happens also to be an
igen Vector of energy then by raising
and lowering until we run out of
possibilities until we run out of until
we hit the end points we create states
of exactly the same
energy this is the idea of degeneracy
following from symmetry when symmetries
don't commute with each
other this is what we talked about in
the beginning when symmetries don't
commute with each each other the L's in
this case it tells us that there are
degeneracies and the degeneracies are
states of equal energy and in this case
the states of equal energy are just
found by going up and down this ladder
in this
way these just States go to the
different axis like the Z axis is
equivalent to the Y AIS yeah yeah
they're they're very closely related to
the idea of taking a state and rotating
it yes that uh for example you could ask
the question what are the igen vectors
of el
subex the igen vectors of el subex are
not individual ones of these but linear
combinations of them right linear
combinations of these are igon vectors
of LX and L
Y and so in that sense what we're
finding here is is um essentially the
igen vectors rotated the rotated
versions of the yeah and that's that's
kind of obvious because when you apply
an L you're generating a
rotation
yeah so this is the Quantum analog of
saying that if you take an
orbit and rotate it about an axis you'll
find a new orbit with a different
angular momentum but with the same
energy different Ang different um Z
component of the angular momentum it's
exactly what's going on here rotating
the configuration is creating states of
different Z compon or different Z
component of the angular momentum but
with exactly the same energy that's
what's
happening Yeah by applying the other
rotation operators now it's convenient
to use these particular combinations l+
and L
minus
uh just because dra figured out how to
do it this
way this is
the um the trick of using raising and
lowering operators and this occurs all
the time in quantum mechanics whenever
you find an algebra like this which
closes on the
commutation that's a signal that uh that
you should be looking for uh creation or
raising and lowering operators and using
the algebra to sort out the spectrum of
the system the spectrum of igen
values that that'll give Zero by
definition that's the definition of the
top level there may not be a top you may
just go up and up and up and up and up
up what's the definition please add that
question how do you define you reach the
top what happens that you know you reach
plus gives
zero andus Z at theot right right now
this can all be made concrete by
specific wave functions uh that show
that this happens I didn't want to write
down complicated angular wave
functions one possibility is you never
run out of anything that would
correspond to basically infinite angular
momentum States states of infinite
angular infinite capacity for but
typically real angular momentum states
of atoms and so forth in
somewhere
um we'll work out more about angular
momentum a little more and then we'll
apply it to atoms and understand a
little bit about Atomic uh
Spectra a little bit about the spectrum
of the hydrogen
atom uh but this is where the
degeneracies or some of the degeneracies
well it's where all of the exact degener
IES of the hydrogen atom come
from all of the equality of
uh
and these states are the
orbital are the various orbital quantum
numbers of um of
uh of the hydrogen
atom there's more there's more but
uh
okay for more please visit us at
stanford.edu